Guide to the George Barr McCutcheon Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
George Barr McCutcheon collection
1876-1928
YCAL MSS 667
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.59
(8 boxes)
The George Barr McCutcheon collection contains writings and other papers relating to the popular early Twentieth-century American novelist and playwright. There are drafts and proofs for a variety of writings, including novels, plays, and articles, dating from roughly 1900 to 1925. The collection features drafts and proofs for several of McCutcheon's novels, ranging from the early Castle Craneycrow (1902) to the penultimate Graustark story, East of the Setting Sun (1925). Other materials include an early penmanship book, a ledger containing detailed publication and financial information on individual works by McCutcheon, and prints and plates for the limited edition My Pictures (1916).
McCutcheon, George Barr, 1866-1928
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by gift and purchase, 1950-1982. For more information consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
George Barr McCutcheon (1866-1928)
George Barr McCutcheon, American novelist and playwright. McCutcheon, who also wrote under the pseudonym of Richard Greaves, was born near Lafayette, Indiana, on 26 July 1866. He was educated at Purdue University and worked as a reporter for the Journal (1889), columnist for the Sunday Journal (1890), and city editor (1893) and part-time staff member, until 1905, at the Courier, all in Lafayette. McCutcheon wrote more than 40 novels, a number of plays and novelettes, and several essays, and is probably best remembered for the Graustark stories. He died 23 October 1928.
Biographical information taken from "George Barr McCutcheon." Twentieth-Century Romance and Historical Writers. Gale, 1994. Gale Biography In Context. Web. 28 Nov. 2012.
Scope and Contents
The George Barr McCutcheon collection contains writings and other papers relating to the popular early Twentieth-century American novelist and playwright. There are drafts and proofs for a variety of writings, including novels, plays, and articles, dating from roughly 1900 to 1925. The collection features drafts and proofs for several of McCutcheon's novels, ranging from the early Castle Craneycrow (1902) to the penultimate Graustark story, East of the Setting Sun (1925). Other materials include an early penmanship book, a ledger containing detailed publication and financial information on individual works by McCutcheon, and prints and plates for the limited edition My Pictures (1916).
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Writings, 1897-1925. II. Other Papers, 1876-1928.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Illustrations (layout features); Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; McCutcheon, George Barr, 1866-1928
- Writings, 1897-1925; Series I; 2.09; (6 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Writings contains drafts and proofs for a variety of writings by McCutcheon, including novels, plays, and articles, dating from roughly 1900 to 1925. The collection features drafts and proofs for several novels ranging from the early Castle Craneycrow (1902) to East of the Setting Sun: A Story of Graustark (1925).
  - "The American Novel," article, printed version, The Sun, 1915 October 16 (Box 1)
  - [ Anderson Crow ?], galley proof, undated (Box 1)
  - Books Once Were Men, article, printed version, The Saturday Evening Post, and case, 1925 September 12 (Box 1)
  - "Buck and Gagg: A Play," draft, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 1)
  - Castle Craneycrow, draft, autograph manuscript, corrected, 1901-1902 (Box 2)
  - East of the Setting Sun: A Story of Graustark, draft, autograph manuscript, corrected, [1923-1924]; 3 (Box 3)
  - "For Pity's Ache: Chapter XII," draft, typescript carbon, undated (Box 3)
  - From the Housetops, galley proof, corrected, circa 1916; 2 (Box 3)
  - From the Housetops, galley proof, corrected, circa 1916 (Box 4)
  - "The Gloaming Ghosts," draft, autograph manuscript and typescript, corrected, 1903 (Box 4)
  - "The Living Monument," article, printed version, undated (Box 4)
  - "My First Party," draft, typescript, undated (Box 4)
  - "Of What Are We Thinking," article, printed version, undated
  - "One Score and Ten," play, galley and page proofs, undated; 2 (Box 4)
  - "A Picture of You," article, printed version, 1918 (Box 4)
  - Quill's Window, galley proof, circa 1921 (Box 4)
  - Shot With Crimson, page proof, circa 1918 (Box 5)
  - Truxton King, draft, autograph manuscript, corrected, 1908 (Box 5)
  - West Wind Drift, galley proof, circa 1920 (Box 5)
  - "Which Twitchcomb?" drafts, autograph manuscript and typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 5)
  - "The Wired End," story, printed version, 1897-1918, undated; 2 (Box 6)
    Includes photographs and printed ephemera
- Other Papers, 1876-1928; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by material type.
  Series II. Other Papers contains an early copy or penmanship book, a ledger containing detailed publication and financial information on individual works by McCutcheon, and prints and plates for the limited edition My Pictures (1916).
  - Literary ledger, circa 1928 (Box 7)
  - Manuscript fragments, undated (Box 7)
  - Penmanship book, completed in manuscript, [1876?] (Box 7)
  - Printed ephemera, 1902-1916, undated (Box 7)
  - Prints and plates for My Pictures, circa 1916; 3 (Box 7)
- Oversize, 1916-1925; 0.08; (1 box)
  - Books Once Were Men, article, printed version, The Saturday Evening Post (In Series I), 1925 September 12 (Box 8)
  - "Of What Were We Thinking," article, printed version (In Series I), undated (Box 8)
  - Manuscript fragment (In Series II), undated (Box 8)
  - Printed ephemera (In Series II), undated (Box 8)
  - Prints for My Pictures (In Series II), circa 1916; 2 (Box 8)